Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adapted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
I can cut a thousand strands of hair
but I cannot sever the tangled threads of my mind.
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Your Highness is back.
His Majesty stopped by just now;
since you were paying respects to Her Majesty,
he said he would come back tonight.
I see.
You just had a scare.
Better to send for Dr. Wen to check on you
to put your mind at peace.
I'm fine.
What happened?
Both of Your Highnesses look upset.
Someone is impatient.
Loose pebbles were scattered on the road back.
The sedan carriers slipped and Huan'er almost fell off.
The sedan was rather high.
If Huan'er did fall,
she would have lost her child.
Is Your Highness all right?
I am.
The stones used for pavement in the palace
were selected carefully.
There shouldn't be any loose pebbles.
Someone must have done this on purpose.
As to the person responsible,
the one residing in the Palace of Great Benevolence
should surely be our first guess.
Who else could be more scheming than she is?
She is most eager
to eliminate other imperial heirs.
Yet so are the concubines.
This will not be their last attempt.
Throughout Your Highness's pregnancy
they will not give up easily.
Taking precautions is not enough to protect us.
Your Highness,
since His Majesty is coming tonight,
you ought to tell him about the incident.
Xiao-Yunzi.
Yes.
Where are the pebbles you picked up?
Here they are.
Find someone reliable in the greenhouse
to examine the lichen on the pebbles.
Yes.
The lichen doesn't seem ordinary to me.
Whoever it was -
there will be consequences for what she did.
His Majesty the Emperor!
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
Your Majesty,
Her Highness is indisposed today
and is sleeping in the bedchamber.
Have you sent for a doctor to check on her?
You should have informed me earlier.
What seems to be the problem? You look unwell.
Your Majesty!
Just hold me like this, please.
Jade.
Your Majesty.
You're Consort Lumière's dowry maid.
Tell me what happened.
Speak the truth.
No one will blame you.
Your Majesty,
My Lady almost fell from her sedan this afternoon
on the way back after visiting
the Empress Dowager with Concubine Vertu.
My Lady had quite a scare.
Why would she almost fall from the sedan?
The carriers accidentally slipped on some loose pebbles.
Where was that？
On the hexagonal stone road near
the Palace of Gathering Excellence.
The hexagonal stones are very slip-resistant.
Why were there loose pebbles on the road?
This matter...
does not simply end with punishing the carriers.
Do you suspect someone attempted to harm you?
Why would I?
I dare not think that way.
I only feel that I'm ill-fated.
Even though Your Majesty bestowed gracious favor on me,
allowing me to serve by your side again,
I'm afraid...
that I don't have the fortune to keep this child.
Nonsense.
Our child is the most blessed.
Of course he will be safe.
What happened today...
was not merely the servants' negligence.
I'm afraid that someone did it on purpose
out of jealousy.
Su Peisheng.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Flog Consort Lumière's sedan bearers thirty times heavily,
then interrogate them thoroughly.
I won't forgive anyone who dares to harm my consort.
Yes.
Please wait, Mr. Su.
Your Majesty,
I don't wish to spread this incident around.
Someone obviously attempted to harm you.
If I don't punish them,
what if something like this happens again?
Even if someone really was targeting me,
I hope Your Majesty can think of it
as their mindless mistake, which I do.
I don't want to disturb the peace in the harem
and upset Your Majesty,
because of me.
Withholding punishment for a mistake ...
especially when it concerns the imperial heir...
it doesn't feel right to me.
Your Majesty,
your benevolence would accumulate
Heaven's blessing for me and our child.
It would also give the offenders
a second chance to rectify themselves.
If they attempt anything again,
the punishment can be combined.
Besides,
it was truly an accident for the sedan bearers.
Could Your Majesty please
forgive them?
Huan Huan,
you are always compassionate and understanding.
Although His Majesty didn't select
a name tag for tonight,
he still hasn't stepped out of the Palace of Eternal Longevity.
Your Majesty should rest.
Consort Lumière is pregnant
and can't serve His Majesty.
Even so, His Majesty still desires her companionship overnight.
The pulse is feeble and floating due to empty fire.
Your Highness must have not been
eating or sleeping well these days.
If I hadn't made the visit myself,
when would Your Highness have sent Lunar for me?
Huan'er almost had an accident soon after her return.
I'm worried, yet I have no clues to guide me.
That's why I haven't been eating or sleeping well.
I'm fine.
You can prescribe some herbs for me and that will do.
Even if Your Highness doesn't
give prime concern to your health,
I can't stop worrying about it.
Your Highness has a cold Stomach.
You must be careful of your diet or you will damage
your Spleen and Stomach, and your overall health.
Luckily it's only me who has
a worried mind and a poor appetite.
What do you mean?
You would be worried if it were Huan'er.
You are both made of flesh and blood.
Of course I would be worried
if Her Highness Consort Lumière were unwell.
But why wouldn't I be when you are?
Your Highness's health takes priority.
I should go back to the Imperial Infirmary
to prepare the prescription for Your Highness.
I'll take my leave.
Your Highness must be tired from the daily visit.
Please sit and rest.
I will pour some tea.
I got the answer.
What is it?
The gardener said the lichen on the pebbles
is a unique kind from Sichuan,
called "calves' hair."
It only grows under dwarf pine trees from
Central Sichuan.
Lady Joie who resides in the Palace of
Gathering Excellence with Concubine Délice
is the only one who cultures dwarf pine bonsai.
Lady Joie is rather pitiful.
She's only a Noble Lady after many
years of service to His Majesty.
Concubine Délice is like a black-eyed chicken
that wants to gulp us down.
Lady Joie might be her accomplice.
My Lady,
why didn't you emphasize this to His Majesty
last night, "when the iron was still hot?"
I wasn't injured after all.
His Majesty wouldn't impose stern punishment
even if he found the culprit.
It's better to set this matter aside for now
and settle the score when more offense occurs.
Your Highness,
Concubine Délice and Lady Joie are here.
I will see them in the main chamber.
- Show them in.
- Yes.
Concubine Délice and Noble Lady Joie
bow in respect before Your Highness.
Peace to Your Highness.
Have a seat.
It has been years since we last met.
Time has treated you well, Délice.
Your Highness's glamour has remained unchanged.
Your time at the temple left hardly a trace.
Is that so?
How harmonious we were when we lived
together in the Palace of Pearl Jade.
It has been three years now.
Your father was close to my father back then.
Who would think he would've secretly contrived to defame my father?
Evidently, people's hearts
change faster than their appearance.
Your Highness's silver tongue
has always been unmatched in the harem.
It's most skilled at "confounding black and white."
When Your Highness wished to return to the palace,
it even talked His Majesty into changing
your Han banner to a Manchu banner.
Is there anything it can't do?
The vast changes I underwent still do not compare to
the heart that "turned from white to black."
I thought that Concubine Délice respected
Your Highness greatly.
She wore her finest ornaments to pay her respects,
including the Red Jade necklace
which the Empress awarded her.
To my surprise,
she sounds sour and bitter just the same.
I haven't seen you for years, Lady Joie.
Peace to Your Highness.
We are old acquaintances.
You need not stand on ceremony.
I thank Your Highness.
Old acquaintances indeed.
But one is now the head of a palace,
the other is merely a Noble Lady
even after so many years.
You came here to pay respects to me.
Concubine Délice, you are the
head of your palace.
Why are you bickering with a resident of your palace?
Isn't that indecorous?
How wise and sensible Your Highness is.
It's a pity that the Palace of Eternal Longevity
is granted to Your Highness exclusively.
Anyone residing in Your Highness's palace
must have accumulated blessings from previous lives.
I was wondering what this was all about.
It turns out that Concubine Joie is bored
living in the Palace of Gathering Excellence
and wants to reside with Consort Lumière.
How hard could this be?
I can make the request to His Majesty for you.
That way you won't feel so desperate
and can stop "singing an opera" to me.
Concubine Délice, you think too highly of yourself.
You will make a request to His Majesty?
Don't you know that His Majesty personally
ordered that the Palace of Eternal Longevity
be occupied exclusively by Her Highness Consort Lumière?
What makes you think that you are capable of
influencing His Majesty to take back his decree?
Huh?
I'm not feeling well.
I won't disturb Your Highness any longer.
I take my leave.
Did Your Highness see?
She is so openly insolent and disrespectful
in your presence.
It's not hard to imagine how much torment
she's made me suffer behind closed doors.
I didn't expect that
your life hasn't been going well, Lady Joie.
It hasn't.
Ever since I moved to the Palace of Gathering Excellence,
She has snared me too many times,
both openly and secretly.
Even though I entered the palace earlier than she did,
I have to submit to her abuse
because she is the head of my palace.
Why haven't you requested to move out of
the Palace of Gathering Excellence?
Concubine Délice is quite favored by the Empress.
Her Majesty would never allow it,
so, how could I ever leave the
Palace of Gathering Excellence?
When I have mentioned this to His Majesty,
he rebukes me for being discontented.
Lady Joie, you came here,
and told me these things.
You must have thought things through.
You may as well speak your mind frankly.
Your Highness is "a direct person who speaks direct words."
I don't want to live under her eaves anymore.
Do you want me to make a request to His Majesty
for you to move out of the Palace of Gathering Excellence?
Instead of living under her eaves and
putting up with her moods,
I'd rather become the head of my own palace someday!
You are ambitious, Joie!
Nonetheless, I have been
practicing Buddhism for many years
and I tend to avoid causing trouble.
I have no one in the harem to rely on,
and my maiden family is thousands of miles away.
Your Highness has now triumphantly returned.
But I dare say there must be bitter hardships behind all the glory.
I'm ready to share Your Highness's hardships
and make my humble contributions.
I appreciate your thoughts, Lady Joie.
But I wish to stay out of all worldly rivalries.
I might not be as capable as I wish to be in some matters.
With Your Highness's rank and influence today,
how could you be incapable?
Besides,
now that Your Highness has returned to the palace,
you can't stay out of the rivalries
however much you wish to avoid them.
Of course,
my visit today was not well planned.
It's only natural if Your Highness has doubts
and needs some time to think it over.
I will think about what you said, Lady Joie.
- Xiao-Yunzi.
- Yes.
Bring in my dwarf pine bonsai.
Yes.
I heard that you are fond of dwarf pine.
So I had one prepared for you today.
Even the pebbles in the pot were carefully selected.
Take a look and see if you like it.
Indeed.
The "calves' hair" on the stones has just the right color.
Everything in Your Highness's palace
is deservedly better than anyone else's.
Violet, take it for me.
Yes.
I'm glad that you like it.
Nevertheless,
it's certainly not as precious as the
red jade necklace that Concubine Délice was wearing.
She ingratiated herself with the Empress.
So Her Majesty personally rewarded it to her.
She wears it most days to show off
that she's in Her Majesty's favor.
But that necklace truly is extraordinary.
It has a unique scent.
Even though you can only faintly catch the scent,
it smells exceptionally good.
What a unique piece, indeed!
Lady Joie has always been unruly.
She provoked a quarrel
as soon as she got the chance.
She made it sound like I've been mistreating her!
Your Highness is the head of this palace.
Your discipline honors her status as a concubine.
If Lady Joie can't recognize that,
Your Highness might as well treat her as your servant.
She's already so insolent now.
Who knows what she will be capable of in the future?
Of course.
She must be pleased with herself
now that Consort Lumière is at her back.
If Consort Lumière didn't have that thing in her belly,
she would be crawling back to
the Forbidden City only in her dreams!
Does Your Highness believe what
Lady Joie said just now?
"Five out of ten."
I couldn't tell from her look
when I gave her the dwarf pine.
If she is guilty,
then she must have learned well
how to conduct herself in the palace.
Did you tell Violet?
I did.
And she said she still has
Your Highness in her thoughts.
She will report back when she gets a chance, My Lady.
I will make up my mind after speaking with her.
The more I think about it, the angrier I feel.
Concubine Délice's insolent face irritates me.
Has she forgotten how she used to
fawn over Your Highness?
Do you think she's stupid?
She knows that given our deep feud,
even if she bowed her head and submitted to me now,
I wouldn't necessarily accept her.
And the Empress would be even more unforgiving.
So she decided to offend me openly
and now I don't know what to do with her.
Regardless, as long as Concubine Délice
follows the Empress,
she won't be able to have a child to secure her future.
Why would you say that, My Lady?
Did you notice her red jade necklace?
Whatever jewels she may have,
our palace has something better.
That necklace is red musk beads.
It looks like red agate,
which is rarely seen in the palace.
After Lady Joie mentioned that it has a scent,
I became certain.
That necklace is made from the glands of male musk deer.
Long term exposure will cause harm through the skin
and lead to infertility.
Then...
Why is she wearing it publicly?
Hasn't anyone warned her?
For one thing, it is quite rare,
so most people don't recognize it.
On the other hand,
didn't you hear Lady Joie say that
it was a reward from the Empress?
Even if the imperial doctors knew,
they would not dare to tell Concubine Délice.
Go to the kitchen
and see if the dishes for Longyue are ready.
I wonder whether or not she will like them.
My Lady, Princess Longyue was away
from you since she was very young.
It's natural that she's grown a little distant.
I am sure it will improve over time.
I hope so.
Have a bite, Princess.
Please eat.
Longyue.
Let me feed her.
Here, Longyue,
let's eat-eat.
Take a bite.
Good. Have some more.
The Princess listens to Your Highness
more than anyone else.
She eats so heartily.
Such a good girl.
- One more bite.
- Grace to Your Highness.
Rise.
This is good timing.
Our kitchen prepared some dishes today.
Consort Lumière thought the
Princess might like them
and asked me to bring them over.
They're so exquisite!
Put them here. Longyue is just about to eat.
I will take my leave then.
Yes.
Here, let's eat more vegetables.
Such a good girl.
His Majesty is most thoughtful towards Your Highness.
The lotuses were specifically
transferred here into these urns,
so Your Highness wouldn't have to walk far
to enjoy them while pregnant.
Lotus flowers are fragrant
and most prone to attract small flies in summer.
Is it the lotus flowers that Your Highness dislikes
or the person who arranged them?
On my birthday that year,
I saw the lake filled with lotus blooms
in the Summer Palace.
No one could match that effort
no matter how hard they tried.
Your Highness, Violet is here.
Bring her in.
Yes.
Peace to Your Highness.
Rise.
I thank Your Highness.
You have slimmed down
now that you're serving Lady Joie.
Is Lady Joie mistreating you?
I don't have the fortune to come back
and serve Your Highness.
When I heard yesterday that Lady Joie was
coming to pay respects to Your Highness,
I was overjoyed and quickly followed her.
I heard that Daisy is gone.
What happened?
Shortly after Your Highness left the palace,
Concubine An said Daisy died suddenly
of some intestinal disease.
Her body was cremated that same night.
But I sneaked a peek before that.
Daisy's mouth and nose were filled with black blood.
She was obviously poisoned.
Even though Daisy was serving Concubine An,
she had come from my palace.
How pitiful that she died this way.
If Lady Joie hasn't been treating you well,
I'll certainly bring you justice.
I thank Your Highness.
After Your Highness left,
I was assigned to serve Lady Joie
and later followed her move to
the Palace of Gathering Excellence.
However, Concubine Délice is the head of that palace.
She resents me for having served
Your Highness in the past
and frequently abuses me verbally and physically.
- Go bring some liniment!
- Yes.
Although I made arrangements
for all of you before I left,
I wasn't able to protect you as much as I wished.
All of you suffered because of me.
It was already Heaven's blessing
that I had served Your Highness.
In other concubines' eyes,
we're just servants living worthless lives.
I am a lowly maid.
How do I deserve Your Highness
doing this for me?
Here,
it'll sting a bit.
But after all, you are Lady Joie's maid.
Why doesn't she speak up for you?
Whenever I was punished, Lady Joie
would argue briefly with Concubine Délice,
to save her own face.
The next time, however,
Concubine Délice would only hit me harder.
The head of a palace has the right to punish
any residents in her palace.
Even though Violet is Lady Joie's maid,
Lady Joie couldn't defend her.
Is it true that Lady Joie and Concubine
Délice have been at odds for a long time?
It is.
I understand your thoughts for me.
Since you're having a hard time serving Lady Joie,
I could find a way to bring you back.
But you know about the feud
between Concubine Délice and me.
Would you be willing to stay at
the Palace of Gathering Excellence for now
to help me keep an eye on them?
Yes, Your Highness.
Your Majesty,
Attendant Service is here.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
I haven't seen Lady Joie for a while.
His Majesty the Emperor.
- Peace to Your Majesty.
- Rise.
Stop! Stop chasing me!
Stay away!
What was that?
Just as before.
Someone come! I'm scared.
Concubine Délice is having nightmares again?
Your Majesty!
Your Majesty, Concubine Délice is having a nightmare.
Will you please come?
Stay away!
Your Majesty!
I'll go over to take a look.
Will Your Majesty come back?
I selected your name tag for tonight.
Of course, I'll be back.
Your Majesty, I just woke up from a nightmare.
My heart is pounding.
Can you please rub my chest for me?
You have had nightmares many times.
Why didn't you call for an imperial doctor
to have a thorough exam?
I've already seen the doctors.
They said that yin is too strong in the palace
and causes my persistent nightmares.
Yin is too strong?
Then I'm the only one in the palace
who has enough yang to balance it out?
Of course.
As the Son of Heaven.
Your Majesty's yang is the strongest
and can overpower anything.
Your Majesty,
why don't you listen to my heartbeat for yourself?
My Lady, why didn't you keep His Majesty here?
His Majesty surely won't return now that he's gone.
His Majesty only visits a few times a year,
and Concubine Délice happens to
have a nightmare every time.
I knew I couldn't stop him.
It's not that I have never tried before.
His Majesty leaves for her anyway.
- Really?
- Yes.
Lady Joie ranks lower and has never been in high favor.
Concubine Délice can't compete with others for favor
yet can easily steal it from Lady Joie.
Whenever His Majesty stays in Lady Joie's residence,
Concubine Délice tries everything
to lure His Majesty away.
Have the Empress and Consort Estime never intervened?
Consort Estime's authority to manage
the harem is in name only.
Her words carry no weight.
To Her Majesty, it's nothing more than
a squabble between two jealous concubines.
The complaints were brushed off
with some perfunctory condemnation.
Idiot.
What?
I should congratulate you, Mother.
That idiot is paving the way for you
to establish authority in the palace.
- Xiao-Yunzi.
- Yes.
Since Concubine Délice claims to have nightmares,
I'll send her a pot of brown rice and Job's tears soup.
Yes.
Remember to send a pot large enough
to fill five big bowls.
Curing Concubine Délice's nightmares is the top priority.
There is no time to cook it thoroughly.
Bring it over once it starts boiling.
Yes.
His Majesty must still be at her place.
Take it over yourself.
She dares not refuse it in front of His Majesty.
I understand.
Exactly, let her have a good drink of her medicine.
Not a drop should be left.
Yes, I will arrange it right away.
You seem to loathe Concubine Délice.
Mother, you're the only one in the palace
who cares about me.
I loathe any snob who takes advantage
of others, and anyone you disapprove of.
Your mistress was inadequate!
You are splashing water around so easily -
so, why didn't you bring His Majesty back
if you're so capable?
Is your heart still racing?
My heart always races when Your Majesty is not here.
Let me hear your heartbeat again?
Your Majesty,
Consort Lumière asked me to deliver
something for Concubine Délice.
What is it? Come inside.
Her Highness heard that Concubine Délice
had a nightmare that affected her heart,
so she ordered me to bring a pot of
brown rice and Job's tears soup.
The doctors said it's the best remedy for nightmares.
Drink it up. It's best for your illness.
I don't want to drink it.
Your Majesty won't come again if I am cured.
Whether I come or not has nothing to do with this.
Consort Lumière cares about your health.
You should drink it.
Please, My Lady.
How could I swallow this thing with brown rice?
No, I won't drink it.
Her Highness said that "Good medicine tastes bitter."
A good remedy is usually unpalatable.
Please consume it for Your Highness's health.
No! Take it away.
If you won't take the medicine,
it means you're not sick,
and you were deceiving me all along.
Her Highness said that it's best to drink it all.
Why did you give Concubine Délice a hard time?
That's just the way she is.
Although shallow and arrogant,
she is still rather adorable.
Your Majesty might think that condoning Concubine
Délice's behavior has no significance.
But everyone else in the harem
would follow suit from now on.
Over time, resentment will inevitably
build up in concubines like Lady Joie,
while those like Concubine Délice
will grow conceited over their favor.
One unpeaceful palace will lead to an unsettled harem.
Won't it cause greater trouble eventually?
I appreciate your prudence and consideration.
As you said,
I should impose a modest punishment on Concubine Délice,
and offer comfort to Lady Joie.
After this,
no concubine in the palace will dare to
grow conceited over her favor.
The Empress Dowager was very pleased
and couldn't stop praising you.
Her Majesty heard about it, too?
Who in the palace hasn't?
"Her Highness Consort Lumière has quite the demeanor."
"She immediately quelled the
improper behaviors in the palace."
The Empress Dowager initially had doubts about you.
Now she trusts you with all her heart.
You don't know the difficulty I had.
If I hadn't used Concubine Délice to set an example,
I wouldn't be able to gain Her Majesty's trust
and prove that I am not a "bewitching minx."
But now that I've made my mark,
someone will hate me for being
a thorn in their side.
It's more important to please
Her Majesty the Empress Dowager.
In Her Majesty's eyes,
my little trick was like "writing in bird-worm script."
Besides, the unhealthy behaviors in the harem
can never be fully cleaned up.
They will only show restraint temporarily.
I'm so unlucky I can't even have a pleasant walk.
My shoes are all covered in mud now.
Please don't be mad, My Lady.
It can harm your health.
Lady Joie is usually reticent.
But when I turned my eyes away from her,
she dared to tell on me.
She is truly "the quiet dog that bites."
Being bitten by this dog brought me all the bad luck.
It's better to endure it for the time being, My Lady.
Even His Majesty is partial to Lady Joie now
to show support for Consort Lumière.
Consort Lumière is a nobody!
Just because His Majesty hasn't
grown tired of her bewitching face,
she thinks she can tread on me!
Better look at herself in the mirror!
She was not satisfied living in a temple
and racked her brains to seduce His Majesty.
What's the big deal with her big belly?
One day she'll know what I'm capable of!
I may not know what you're capable of,
but I know the walls have ears.
Concubine Délice,
you'd better take care of yourself.
The time you're wasting on grouching and grumbling
could've been better spent on taking
more brown rice and Job's tears soup
to treat your nightmares.
Consort Lumière... It is Consort Lumière!
Be quiet, My Lady.
Mother,
you're not upset?
Remember,
don't ever waste time and energy on
anyone or anything unworthy.
Yes.
A distinguished guest is here.
I should have been welcoming you far outside the door.
Honnête, you look much healthier over the years.
Thank you, Lumière. Please.
With Wenyi in my life,
the long days are much easier to pass.
Otherwise, I would be dragging myself
from year to year
with nothing to look forward to.
You are so lucky.
My Longyue...
isn’t close to me.
Consort Estime loves Longyue
even more than I love Wenyi.
After all, Longyue was raised by her since birth
and naturally feels closer to her.
Right now, Consort Estime cannot put her mind at ease.
To put myself in her state of mind,
I imagine if Concubine Aide came back to life
and asked to take Wenyi back,
I would also be extremely reluctant.
I understand.
Consort Estime is a sensible person.
But no matter how sensible one is,
one can't fight love.
Not to mention it is a mother's love for her daughter.
You don't know what happened while you were away.
One year,
Longyue was sick.
Consort Estime didn't sleep for days on end.
Had Longyue not been saved at that time,
I'm afraid Consort Estime would've
died from a broken heart as well.
Even though I am her birth mother,
I truly didn't provide her any motherly care.
How can I expect Longyue to be close to me?
I only hope
that she will recognize me as her mother one day.
Even I think it's wrong and unfair
if you say that you didn't provide her any motherly care.
Back then,
you left the palace only three days
after giving birth to Longyue.
In those three days, you racked your brain
and exhausted all of your thoughts
to plan for her entire future.
Nevertheless,
I still need to offer this advice.
Don't rush to take Longyue back to your palace.
Even though you miss your daughter dearly,
you have to bear it.
You returned to the palace as a Niohuru.
You should stay away from the daughter
of Concubine Souire from the Zhen family
to keep gossip down.
I'll keep your words in mind.
Look at you, you are sweating.
How about I take you to the Thousand Carp Pond?
Yes.
Consort Lumière.
Longyue, hurry up and greet Her Highness.
Greetings, Your Highness.
Can Mother take you to play together?
No, No ...
Longyue was playing and was interrupted
so she doesn't want to be picked up.
After hearing about moving to live with you,
she cried for a whole day.
Why not let her stay at the Palace of
Universal Happiness for a few more days?
Estime, what are you talking about?
She's your child.
Of course, she will live with you in the
Palace of Universal Happiness.
I only wanted to play with her for a while.
We are heading to the Thousand Carp Pond
to feed the fish.
Why don't you come with us?
I have things to attend to in my palace.
Please enjoy your time with Longyue.
Longyue, say goodbye to your Mother.
Don't be angry, Your Highness.
What's there to be angry about?
It's a good thing that the princess has
one more person who loves her.
But Consort Estime seems to have forgotten
who the princess's birth mother is.
Just now, Consort Estime invited Your Highness
to feed the fish with the princess.
Wouldn't it have been a good chance
to get close to the princess?
If Consort Estime genuinely wanted to invite me,
she would have asked as soon as we met.
Besides, they're savoring their time together
as mother and daughter.
If I went along,
who knows how many more rifts would be created?
What's the point of that?
Consort Estime was not wrong.
Longyue's birth mother is Zhen.
I am Niohuru.
How can I be her birth mother?
Lumière.
Greetings, Lumière.
It's been a long time since we last met.
You've become a distinguished concubine now.
You are the truly distinguished one.
I originally thought that you would have to
live a harsh and lonely life outside.
I was so worried about you.
But things turned like the mountain road twists.
Now you live in an elevated moment,
bringing another heir to the family.
No one can have a truly perfect moment.
There are always imperfections in life.
Even though you have advanced to Concubine
and head your own palace,
there must be times when things
don't go the way you wish.
Since you left I have been serving His Majesty in your place.
Yet I still don't have a child.
I have to say I'm not blessed by Heaven.
Even so, the daughter you gave birth to
is now someone else's child.
How does that make you feel?
Longyue hasn't lived with me since birth.
It’s not surprising that she’s not close to me.
But I believe
that there is a gain for every loss in life.
In comparison,
I am a little more fortunate than you, to get pregnant quickly.
There is a gain for every loss.
I'm only worried that the gain
won't cover your loss.
I agree with you.
In the meantime,
some people tried their utmost to scheme,
only to lose everyone's trust and support.
I’m afraid that...
they're "drawing water with a sieve"
and all their efforts were in vain.
I couldn't agree more.
I also heard that you almost fell
from the sedan the other day
when passing the Palace of Gathering Excellence.
Thankfully you were not hurt.
I was "rubbing my sweating hand" for you.
The Palace of Gathering Excellence, you said?
Lady Joie has served His Majesty for a long time.
It's understandable that she has developed some fire.
Do you really believe it was done by Lady Joie?
If you think about it carefully,
who in the Palace of Gathering Excellence
has a long-standing feud with you?
What her father did is a separate issue.
She hasn't done anything to me personally.
It's benevolent of you to think that way.
But she has always wanted to replace you.
How can you not understand?
She is most favored by the Empress.
How dare you speak against her
behind her back without any evidence?
I’ve made too many mistakes in the past
and have also seen many made by others.
There are things that I would let "rot in my stomach."
But you were targeted by someone
soon after your return.
How could I hold it back from you now?
The mistakes I made in the past are now cast in stone.
I only wish to make some compensations today.
I don’t know ... how I should consider this.
In His Majesty's eyes,
you are the quietest and most obedient one.
Are you saying that
you have also had underhanded dealings in the past?
If you say that, does that mean you are
unwilling to forgive me?
I don’t know how to read minds in the palace.
However, Lingrong,
we have known each other like sisters for so many years.
I will never be able to do enough penance
for my sins in this life.
I only hope you can give birth to the imperial heir
safe and sound.
Please be extra careful about everything.
What a nice fragrance.
Lady Joie gave me this sachet.
Do you like the scent?
I understand what you mean.
I will be careful.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Phoenix Taking Flight
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
The dreams I dimly recall;
The past I hardly remember,
amidst the autumn moons and the spring flowers.
Like the moon's reflection on water
or flowers seen through mist - floating and drifting.
The joyous sounds you brought;
The silence you left;
Changing faster than clouds can turn to rain.
Our minds resonated;
Our hearts beat in unison;
But we lost what we once possessed.
A poem to converse;
A melody to accompany;
A heart to bind to mine.
I hoped for endless longing and eternal promise,
but I’m left with only the flute and the zither.
With affection, I pleased;
With my heart, I committed;
With my arms, I embraced.
I desired to be remembered;
Desired to be cherished;
Why am I only hated and deceived?
My wish ran against my will.
Behold the mockery of destiny and the game of fate.
My unwavering love is gone
like flowers swept away in the wind.
Praying for a bright moon;
Praying for a rising sun;
Dreaming to bask in the spring breezes.
But the unsparing northern winds carry snow and rain
to destroy the aspirations of the plum tree.
A phoenix about to take flight rustles its wings
but the arc of its flight is unseen.
The phoenix tree sways in the wind,
shedding memories in the whispers of the falling leaves.